A Guide to the Papers of Thomas Perkins Abernethy, 1585 (1947-1965) 1969
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Thomas Perkins Abernethy 1585 (1947-1965) 1969
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12765-a
This collection consists of ca. 2,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was presented to the library on July 29, 1974 by Thomas P. Abernethy, 39 University Circle, Charlottesville, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
The Thomas Perkins Abernethy Collection consists of approximately four linear feet (ca. 2,000 items) spanning the years 1585 (1947-1965) 1969. Included in the collection of the historian are drafts of many of the articles and book reviews he has written, as well as of his book The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819. The original collection, #6464, consists of a carbon copy of the publisher's draft of The South In the New Nation. Correspondence with fellow historians and students, speeches, and miscellaneous papers including some dealing with the Corcoran Department of History of the University of Virginia comprise the rest of the collection. There are transcripts and Photostats of letters and documents for the dates 1585, 1621, 1722, 1797, and 1804- 1806, and there are a few letters and some printed material for the 1920's through the early 1940's, but the bulk of the collection falls between the years 1947 and 1965.
Thomas Perkins Abernethy [1890- ] was born in Lowndes County, Alabama. He received an A. B. degree from the College of Charleston in 1912, and his M. A. (1915) and Ph.D. (1922) degrees from Harvard University, where he studied under Frederick Jackson Turner. He taught at Vanderbilt University, the University of Chattanooga, and the University of Alabama before coming to the University of Virginia in 1930. During his long tenure at Virginia, he served as chairman of the History Department from 1946-1955, advised a large number of graduate students, and wrote numerous books and articles before retiring in July of 1961.
The material in this collection chiefly reflects Abernethy's career as professor and scholar at the University of Virginia. Personal and family correspondence is almost entirely lacking. There are research notes for his book The Burr Conspiracy and several drafts of The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819, but the manuscripts of his other books are missing. There is little material from Abernethy's early years as a professor.
Arrangement
When the collection came to the library, much of the original filing order had been lost. As a result, the correspondence has been filed by academic year, (September of one year through August of the next) and alphabetized by correspondent within each year. The correspondence is followed by Albernethy's writings, including articles, book reviews, and drafts of his book The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819. These are followed by the rest of Abernethy's papers, including research notes, student papers, and miscellaneous printed material. Six file boxes contain bibliographies and indexes for his books on 3 x 5" note cards.
File Boxes
1. Bibliography and research notes on British designs on North America
2. Bibliography for The Burr Conspiracy
3. Bibliography for unidentified book
4. Index for The South In the New Nation, A - L
5. Index for The South In the New Nation, M - Z
6. Index for unidentified book
Contents List
- Frederick Jackson Turner to TPA 1926 March 12, Transcript & carbon (Box 1)
- Robert B. Tunstall to TPA 1932 July 29, TLS (Box 1)
- Mary D. Carter to TPA 1935 Oct. 21, TLS (Box 1)
- Mary D. Carter to TPA 1936 Feb. 28, TLS (Box 1)
- TPA to E. I. Carruthers 1936 Sept. 23, TL (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1940 March-April, 2 items (Box 1)
- TPA to E. I. Carruthers 1946 Oct. 23, TL (carbon) (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1947 Sept. -1948 Aug., 4 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1948 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 47 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1949 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 50 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1950 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 30 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1951 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 75 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1952 Sept. -1948 Aug., 8 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1953 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 25 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1954 Sept. -1948 Aug., 16 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1955 Sept. -1948 Aug., 13 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1956 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 90 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1957 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 120 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1958 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 60 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence: A - M 1959 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 55 items. (Box 2)
- Correspondence P - W 1959 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 35 items. (Box 2)
- Correspondence: A - K 1960 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 75 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence: L - W 1960 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 100 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence: A - L 1961 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 75 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence 1961 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 60 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence 1962 Sept. -1948 Aug., 20 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence 1963 Sept. -1948 Aug., ca. 50 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence 1964 Sept. -1948 Aug., 3 items (Box 3)
- Curtis Carroll Davis to TPA 1969 March 21, TLS (Box 3)
- Correspondence n. d., 8 items (Box 3)
- Article(?) by TPA: "Aaron Burr in Mississippi" "The Burr Conspiracy""Democracy and the Southern Frontier""The Southern Shores and the Maritime Menace, 1793-1812""The Yazoo Land Companies of 1789" 1949 and n. d., 15 items (Box 3)
- Biographical sketches by TPA of Aaron Burr, Roger Atkinson, Robert Augustus Toombs, Henry Alexander Wise n. d., 9 items (Box 3)
- "The Political Geography of Southern Jacksonism" by TPA 1931 Jan., 1 item (Box 3)
- Book Reviews by TPA, 18 items (Box 3)
- Reprints of Articles by TPA: "Commerical Activities of Silas Deane in France" "Journal of the First Kentucky Convention""The Orgin of the Franklin - Lee Imbroglio""An Historical Sketch of the University of Virginia""The First Transmontane Advance", 5 items (Box 3)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819, Title page, Table of Contents (with 22 chapters) List of Maps and charts, Preface: Preliminary draft 1961, TMs & TMs (carbon) (Box 4)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. I - II, Preliminary draft 1961, TMs w/holograph corrections (Box 4)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. III - V (eliminated from published edition) 1961, TMs w/holograph corrections (Box 4)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. VI - VIII (Chaps. III - V of published edition) Preliminary draft 1961, TMs w/holograph corrections (Box 4)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. XII - XIII (Chaps. IX - X in published edition) Preliminary draft 1961, TMs w/holograph corrections (Box 4)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. XIV (Chap. XI of published edition) Preliminary draft 1961, TMs w/holograph corrections (Box 5)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. XV - XVI (Chaps. XII - XIII of published edition) Preliminary draft 1961, TMs w/holograph corrections (Box 5)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. XVIII (eliminated from published edition) Preliminary draft 1961, TMs w/holograph corrections (Box 5)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. XIX - XX (Chaps. XIV - XV of published edition) Preliminary draft 1961, TMs w/holograph corrections (Box 5)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. XXI (eliminated from published edition) Preliminary draft 1961, TMs w/holograph corrections (Box 5)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. XXXI (Chap XVI in published edition) and critical essay on authorities Preliminary draft 1961, TMs w/holograph corrections (Box 5)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Discarded portions and holograph footnotes for preface, Chaps. I - X 1961, TMs w/holograph corrections (Box 5)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Discarded portions and holograph or typed footnotes for Chaps. XI - XXII 1961, TMs w/holograph corrections (Box 6)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Table of contents with 16 chapters, list of maps and charts (incomplete), preface Publisher's draft 1961, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 6)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chap. II, Publisher's draft 1961, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 6)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. VI - IX (Chaps III - VI of published edition) Publisher's draft 1961, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 6)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. X - XIII (Chaps VII - X of published edition) Publisher's draft 1961, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 6)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. XIV - XVI (Chaps XI - XIII of published edition) Publisher's draft 1961, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 6)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Chaps. XIX -XXII (Chaps XIV XVI of published edition) Publisher's draft 1961, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 6)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Critical essay on authorities and index Publisher's draft 1961, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 7)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 List of topics and description of manuscript 1961, 5 items (Box 7)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 Title page, Dedication page, & Table of Contents 1961, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 7)
- The South In the New Nation: 1789-1819 1st Draft of Introduction 1961, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 7)
- Southern Frontier of the War of 1812 2nd Draft of Introduction 1968, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 7)
- Southern Frontier of the War of 1812 Chaps. II - III Preliminary draft 1968, TMs(carbon) (Box 7)
- Southern Frontier of the War of 1812 3rd Draft of Introduction 1968, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 7)
- Southern Frontier of the War of 1812 Revised portions of Chap. I 1968, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 7)
- Southern Frontier of the War of 1812 Chaps II - III, Notes, Sources of Information Revised draft 1968, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 7)
- Southern Frontier of the War of 1812 Discarded portions of Introduction and Chap. II 1968, TMs(carbon) (Box 7)
- Southern Frontier of the War of 1812 Notes 1968, TMs(carbon) w/holograph corrections (Box 7)
- Southern Frontier of the War of 1812 Abernethy's reply to Reader's Report and Miscellaneous Notes 1968, 3 items (Box 7)
- Speeches of Abernethy: "The Creed of the Old South" "Comments on Virginia's Contribution to American Civilization""Mr. Jefferson's Fourth Freedom" "The Order of Cape Henry""Making History""The Sad Plight of History In the South""The Social Scene in Virginia""Virginia's Western Land Policy During the Revolution""Charlottesville's Historic Area" n. d., 9 items (Box 7)
- Corcoran Department of History: Financial Papers including invoices, allotment balances, Fellowship funds 1947-1952, ca. 150 items. (Box 7)
- Corcoran Department of History: Miscellaneous Papers including Annual Reports, Class Rolls, Resumes of students 1947-1952, ca. 30 items (Box 7)
- Genealogical Chart of early generations of the Abernethy family in Virginia and North Carolina n. d., 1 item (Box 8)
- Newspaper Clippings 1924-1964, ca. 45 items (Box 8)
- Photostats of 2 letters from Aaron Burr, also photostats of Spanish transcripts of letters primarily between Col. Antonio Cordero and Memesio de Salcedo and Nemesio de Salcedo and of soldier's account of Zebulon Pike expedition 1804-1806, ca. 15 items (Box 8)
- Proofs of illustrations of Gen. T. J. Jackson and University of Va. Also Theodore O'Hara and Gen. George MacGregor n. d., 9 items (Box 8)
- Purchase lists for Tracy W. McGregor Library, Rare Book Department, Alderman Library, University of Virginia and Description of Jefferson Papers in McGregor Library 1948-1952, 1957-1958, 15 items (Box 8)
- Receipts, Financial papers 1949-1964, ca. 25 items (Box 8)
- Research Notes and Transcripts collected for The Burr Conspiracyn. d., 14 items (Box 8)
- Student Papers of Caroline Cook and H. Charles Lilienfeld of University of Alabama 1930, 2 items (Box 8)
- Student Papers of William L. Kirby and John E. Manahan 1946, 2 items (Box 8)
- Student Papers of Flora A. Ballowe, Phyllis Honeycutt, Gerald Special, and Thomas Bowles Shiflet 1954, 4 items (Box 8)
- Student Papers of James M. Efird and Daniel L. Gribbs, Jr. n. d., 2 items (Box 8)
- Letters and papers re the South 1585, 1621, 1722, 1797, 1952, n. d., ca. 10 items TMss(carbon) & Transcripts (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous Papers 1938-1964, ca. 50 items (Box 9)
- Near Print and Printed Material re Colonial period, American Revolution, the Confederation period, and the early National period ca. 1930-1960, 12 items (Box 9)
- Near Print and Printed Material re Colonial period, American Revolution, the Confederation period, and the early National period ca. 1930-1960, 15 items (Box 9)
- Periodicals re Colonial period 1929-1939, 5 items (Box 9)
- Near Print and Printed Material re the South, Slavery and the Civil War ca. 1850-1940, ca. 25 items (Box 10)
- Near Print and Printed Material re the South, Slavery and the Civil War ca. 1950-1965, ca. 10 items (Box 10)
- Miscellaneous Printed Material ca. 1940-1960, ca. 15 items (Box 10)
- Miscellaneous Printed Material ca. 1873-1956, 12 items (Box 10)